你好黑客
hello hackers
我是Yan，欢迎来到Pwn学院
I'm Yan welcome to Pwn College
今天我们要讲的是
Today we're going to be talking about
内存，我们汇编课程一部分
memory as part of our Assembly crash course
我们讲过数据
so we talked about data
讲过寄存器
we talked about registers
我们把数据存在这里，方便快速使用
where we hold data to quickly work on it
寄存器很少
now there's very few registers right
因为它们很贵
because they're expensive
它们必须紧靠CPU
they need to be right next to the CPU
这样CPU才能直接访问它们
so the CPU can directly access them
它们需要放在CPU里
they need to be inside the CPU
而这里没有太多的空间
and there's just not a lot of space in there
这里很挤
it's very very cramped
所以每隔一段时间
so every once in a while
当运行的太多时
when we have too much stuff going on
有太多的数据时
too much data
我们需要把数据放到内存
we need to put it in memory
内存是一个巨大的数据保险库
now memory is a big vault of data
就像银行的保险箱一样
like a safety deposit box vault in a bank
我们把数据，放入数字标记的抽屉
where we just go and we put the data into a number slot
还记得在第一讲中提到的CPU架构吗
remember our crazy CPU architecture from the first lecture
我们现在讨论的是这个
we're talking about this right here
CPU是如何获取数据的
now how does the CPU get at data
这超出了这门课的范围
it's kind of outside the scope of this class
但基本上
but basically
需要数据时
data when it is needed
当它被CPU请求时
when it's requested by the CPU
会经过某种桥
goes over some crazy sort of bridge
来到一层CPU缓存
into a one level of cache
再从那层缓存进入下一级缓存
goes from that cache into another level of cache
然后从缓存进入寄存器
and it goes from that cache into the registers
然后直接被控制单元使用
and then used directly by the control unit
或者是CPU的算术单元
or the arithmetic unit of the CPU
这个过程需要时间
this takes time
所以我们希望数据尽可能多的放在寄存器中
and so we want to work on registers as much as possible
等需要的时候直接用
and then go to data when we need
我们确实这么做了
and we do
不确定有几个，总之寄存器很少
I mean like I don't remember very few registers
但要存储的数据很多
but there's a lot of data to cover
16个通用寄存器
like 16 general purpose registers
加上很多其他的寄存器
and a bunch of other ones
但想看的猫咪视频有数TB
but we might need terabytes of cat videos that we need to watch
好吧
all right
我们来谈谈内存
let's talk about memory
从进程的角度看
so from a process perspective
进程做什么都要用内存
your process uses memory for everything
它用内存保存与恢复寄存器
it uses memory to store and load registers
它用内存从硬盘读数据
it uses memory actually to read data from the disk
写数据到硬盘
write to the disk
所有要在内存、网卡、显卡之间传数据的时候
and all like shunting data around memory the network card the video card
内存有很多
there's a lot of memory
不能给每个内存地址起名
and there's just too much memory to add to name every location
寄存器可以
there's enough registers to name every register
如RAX、RBX、RCX等等
RAX RBX RCX etc
但内存就太多了，不能这么干
but there is too much memory to do so
所以内存就用的数字
so memory has numbers
就比如
it's similar as like
大学太大了，无法通过名字来管理每个人
a university's too big that to track everyone by name
他们给每个人一个学生ID
they give everyone a student ID
或员工ID
or an employee ID you know
内存也用数字标识符
memory has these numerical identifiers
内存基本上是
now memory is basically
用0到一个非常大的数字，线性编址
addressed linearly from zero to a very very high number
它曾经差不多是架构的字长
it used to be more or less the word width of architecture
现在它实际上是
now it's actually something
其实也不是
well that's actually not
总之，现在它从
anyways now it is from
(详见mmap_min_addr)
实际没从0开始
it's actually not from zero
从0开始会带来很多安全问题
it's there's a lot of security issues that happen
如果你能访问地址0
if you can access memory at zero
又不小心保留了一个初始化为0的指针
then if you accidentally leave an address initialized to zero
这是有可能的
that stuff can happen
(0x0000 0000 0001 0000 ~ 0x0000 7FFF FFFF FFFF）
用户态内存从0x10000到2^47
but it goes to 2 to the 47th for your process memory
然后是内核态内存
and then for your kernel memory
进程内存中给操作系统用的那部分
for your operating system part of your processes memory
从2^47 + 1
goes from 2 to 47 minus 1（口误）
(0xFFFF 8000 0000 0000~0xFFFF FFFF FFFF FFFF)
到2^48(忽略为1的高16位)
and then for your process memory it goes from 2 to 47th all the way to 2 to 48 minus 1
总之
anyways
这是一块巨大的内存
this is an enormous amount of memory
这是127TB的可寻址内存
that's 127 terabytes of addressable RAM
内存可以映射在这里的任意地址
you can have RAM kind of live anywhere in here
都可以放
that there's memory
没人有这么大的物理内存
no one has that much RAM
就算你花大价钱
I don't even think you can spin up a
也创建不了这么大内存的云主机
massive cloud machine for insane amounts of money with that much RAM
这是很大的内存
it's a lot of RAM
我忘了提，每一个
I forgot to mention each of these
每个地址
each location each numbered location
表示1字节的内存
represents 1 byte of memory
即8位
8 bits
没这么多内存，为啥有这么多地址
so how can you have this much memory addresses if you have not this much RAM
并不是所有内存都是真的
well not all of your memory is real
事实上，我们使用的是虚拟内存
in fact we use something called virtual memory
稍后我们将深入了解虚拟内存
we'll learn a lot about virtual memory later
在后面讨论内核安全的模块中
in a later module and talk about kernel security
你会明白它的原理
you'll understand exactly how it works
超级酷
it's super cool
每个进程都有它的虚拟内存空间
but we have every process has its virtual memory space
一开始只有部分填充
and it starts out just partially filled
程序代码会放在这儿
it's the processes program data is gonna go somewhere
放在这儿的是动态分配的内存
somewhere else is gonna be its dynamically allocated memory
即，堆
the heap
这儿是库代码
somewhere else is gonna be some library code
栈
the stack
其他操作系统辅助区域
other operating system helper regions
你的进程内存中有很多东西
there's a bunch of stuff in your
进程随时可以映射更多内存
your process can request more memory to be mapped in at any time
这基本就是进程的内存视图
and this is basically the view of memory of your process
请求内存就是，进程直接说
and it just says hey
我想要这块地址的内存
I want memory at this region at this address
然后拿到它
and then it grabs it
首先我们来谈谈栈
so first let's talk about the stack
然后我们会谈到
and then we'll talk about
如何在寄存器和内存之间传递值
how to move values between registers and memory
当然，用栈也是其中一种方式
well I mean the stack is one such way
栈是一个内存区域
the stack is a region of memory
进程启动时
that when your process starts up
希望你们还记得进程生命周期系列视频
and hopefully you recall our whole lecture series about process lifecycle
当进程启动时
when a process starts up
会在内存中创建一个称为栈的空间
a space in memory is created called the stack
它在某个地址上
and it is at some address
这个地址通常是一个怪值
and that address is usually something absurd like
我们一会儿再谈它
whatever we'll talk about it in a second
当你想保存寄存器的值时
when you want to store a register
或想临时存储一个值到栈上时
or a value in memory on the stack for temporary storage
你可以push它
you can push it
把它压入栈
you push things onto the stack
之后再把它们弹出栈
and then you pop them right back off the stack
这里我压入了三个值
so here I push three values
我把0xc001ca75写入RAX
I push I write c001 ca75 into RAX
然后压入栈
and then I push cool cats
再压入0xb0ba cafe
then I push b0ba cafe
到这里了
push Boba Cafe
再压入rax
and I push RAX
在这里
push Rax
之后我可以逆序弹出它们
and then later I can pop them right back off in reverse order
我弹出栈顶的值时
and so when I pop the top value of this
这些值没有身份标识
now these are values they have no identity
它们不记录和原来有关联的寄存器
they maintain no identity back to the original register
如存放它们之类的关系
in which they were stored or whatever
被压入栈的只有0，1组成的值
there're just ones and zeros pushed onto the stack
栈上一个单元的长度是机器字长
each entry on the stack is the bitwidth of the architecture
每个单元64位
each entry 64 bits
即使我压入一个32位的数，也会用0填充
even if I push the 32 bit number just zero pads it
现在即使是在64位cpu上
now even on 64 bit CPUs as it says here
具体来说是x86的cpu
oh x86 specifically
只能压入32位立即数
you can only push 32 bit numbers
没有直接压入64位数字的指令
there's just no instruction to push a 64 bit numbers directly
这真让人恼火
it's very infuriating
你必须这样
you have to do this
先把它写进寄存器，然后再压入它
you have to write it to a register and then push it
他们就是没做相应的指令
they just didn't make an instruction for it
我觉得这很蠢，但咋说呢
which I think it's dumb but whatever
我又没研发amd64
I didn't make AMD64
他们可能有很好的理由
and they probably had good reasons
可能也没人需要这个
and probably no one needs this anyways
好吧，除了汇编老师
alright except for like assembly teachers
关键是能把值放栈上
so point is we have values on the stack
也能拿出来
we can pop them off
还有值是逆序弹出的
and they are popped in reverse order
你可以想象
you can imagine
实际上，栈应该被想象为
in fact the stack should be imagined as
一叠游戏
like a stack of video games
你把它压到栈上
you push onto the stack
压入栈
push onto the stack
然后以相反的顺序弹出栈
then you pop off the stack in reverse order
由于栈位于连续的内存空间中
now since the stack lives in a continuous memory space
我喜欢从左到右阅读
and I like to read from left to right
所以从右往左画
I write it out from left to right
稍后会讨论为什么我把值放在右侧
and we'll talk about why I put stuff on the right of it in a second
我压入了rax，它的值为c001 ca74
I pushed rax the value in that cool cats
如同mov
of course like mov
寄存器中还有值
the value stays also in the register
现在2个地方都有值
now it's in two places
然后我压入了b0ba cafe
then I pushed Boba Cafe
然后我又压入了c001 ca75
then I pushed Cool Cats again
这是现在的栈
this is my stack
等我弹出值到RBX时
when I pop into RBX
这会把c001 ca75
it's going to take coolcats
从栈中移除
it's going to take it off the stack
有趣的是，它还在栈上
actually fun fact it remains on the stack
只是重新定义了栈的结束位置
we just redefine where the stack ends
要是你想读取它们，数据还在那里
but the bytes are still there if you wanted to get at them
然后我们把这个值写进RBX
and then we write the value that was there into rbx
所以RBX变成了c001 ca75
so in here RBX becomes Cool Cats
然后弹出数据到RCX
and then when we pop into RCX
RCX变成了b0ba cafe
RCX becomes Boba Cafe
就是这么简单
it's that simple
没问题
push pop no problem
栈非常简单
the stack very simple
我们来谈谈地址
let's talk about addressing
现在栈在内存的某个地址上
now the stack is in somewhere in memory at an address
这个地址通常是0x7f跟着一长串
that address is typically 0x7f followed by a bunch of garbage
因为它通常是做了随机化的
because it's typically randomly located
为什么它开头是7F
why is it there at 7F specifically
没有真正的原因
there's no real reason
你可以把栈放在任何地方
you could place the stack anywhere really
栈位于内存中非常高的部分
the stack is in very high parts of memory
因为历史原因
because historically and here is a crazy thing
它会反向增长
it grows backwards
压栈时，栈会向小地址增长
it grows toward smaller memory addresses as you push onto the stack
比如，rsp中是这个050结尾的地址
if RSP starts out at this crazy address ending in hex 050
栈里有c001 ca75
and it has cool cats on it
我们再压入b0ba cafe
and we push Boba Cafe
c001 ca75在050处
Cool Cats was at address 050
b0ba cafe的地址是048
Boba Cafe now lives at address 048
它现在是新栈顶
which coincidentally is the new top of the stack
就是栈的最左侧
as its term really the left part side of the stack
rsp中的地址
and the address of the stack in the register that stores the address of the stack
减小了8
is decreased by 8
当你把寄存器压入栈时，rsp减小8
when you push onto the stack the registers decrease by 8
因为栈向内存的开始方向，即向左，增长
because the stack grows to the left toward the beginning of memory
顺便说一下，我的视频是镜像的
and my video may be mirrored by the way
我真的应该把它修好，这太蠢了
I should really fix that that's dumb all right
我们越
the more we
弹栈时
when we pop
我们把这个值写入rcx
then we take that value we write that into RCX
然后更新rsp
and then we fix up the stack pointer again
这样它保存的地址还是以050结尾
so that it holds the address ending in 050
恢复到我们压栈前
what we started before we pushed
总之
TooLong;Didn'tRead
push时，rsp减8
push subtracts 8 from RSP
pop时，rsp加8
pop adds 8 to RSP after writing and reading the data respectively
你可以直接使用rsp中的地址访问内存
you can access memory using its addresses directly
就是要小心
just be careful
确保那里有东西可以访问
make sure that there's something there to access
内存是虚拟的
again memory is virtual
当尝试访问时，它可能不存在
it might not exist when you try to access
你的程序就会崩溃
your program will crash
事实上，如果你运行这个程序，它肯定会崩溃
in fact if you run this it definitely crash
这基本上是在说，嘿
but this basically says hey
把0x12345这个地址
take this address 0x12345
放到rax中
move it into rax
然后把它当作内存地址
then use it as a memory address
查看内存
look at the memory
这就是这个方括号的意思
and that's what these brackets mean
方括号的意思是
the brackets mean hey there's
这是一个内存地址
this is a memory address
查看该内存地址的数据
look at the data in memory
读入到RBX
and read it into RBX
RBX是64位寄存器
RBX is a 64 bit register
它将从rax地址处的内存读取64位，8字节
so it will read 64 bits 8 bytes from rax
内存一次存储一个字节
memories stores a byte a time
虽然读3比特的内存也是有意义的
though it does make sense to read like 3 bits of memory
一次可以读取几个字节或1字节
you read memory several bytes at a time or one byte at a time
这将把8字节数据读入RBX
so this will read 8 bytes into RBX
8个字节的地址将从0x12345开始
and the 8 bytes will start from 0x12345
这将存储rax中的8字节
all right this will store 64 bits 8 bytes that are in rax
抱歉，rbx中的8字节
no sorry in RBX whatever they were
放到0x133337地址开始的内存中
into the memory space starting at the address 133337
和读取内存一样
so in the same way as the read
数据流向
again information data flows to the
镜像了
with the mirror
左边
to the left
之前我们取出rax指向的内存数据
we take the memory in rax
再放到rbx中
and here we read it into RBX
加载到rbx中
we load it
这里取出rbx的数据
this takes the data in RBX
然后保存到rax作为地址指向的内存
and we store it into the memory address by RAX
现在重要的是这里的值
now it's the value here that's important
如果这个值是在RCX中
if this value was in RCX
这里是RCX
and we had RCX here
那么它会指向相同的内存
it would point to the same memory
现在我一直用“指向”这个词
now I keep using the word point to
寄存器中存一个内存地址
an address in a register of a given memory address
意味着寄存器指向这个内存地址
means that that register points that memory address
相当于，说
saying ha ha ha
它在那儿，它在那儿
there it is there it is
那里就是我们要写入的地址
that's where we're gonna write
那里就是我们要读取的地址
that's where we're gonna read
就是这样
that's it
这就是指针的意思
that's all the pointer means
一个有趣的例子
we have a interesting case where we can also
指针意味着
pointer means that
寄存器中有一个地址，它指向了一个内存位置
there's an address in a register that references some memory location
RSP是扩展后的sp栈指针
well hey RSP is the really extended stack pointer
rsp就像我们刚刚说的那样
rsp as we talked about just now
保存着内存中栈的地址
holds the address of the stack
你也可以直接访问它
you can also access it directly
这没什么特别的
nothing special about this
这相当于push
this is equivalent to a push
这里不对
actually this is a lie
应该是8
this should be 8
我的锅
my bad
我暂停修正一下
let me pause the recording and fix that
因为这样才对
because that should be correct
好了，我们回来了，现在对了
alright we're back so now it's correct
RSP减去8
subtracting 8 from RSP
然后输入你想要压入的值
and then plopping whatever value you wanted to push
这相当于push
this is equivalent to push
很酷，对吧
pretty cool alright
记住，每个内存地址能放1字节
and remember each memory location contains 1 byte
所以如果你写入一个8字节的值到0x133337处
and so if you write an 8 byte value 64 bit value to 133337
你会往0x133337处（写入1字节）
you will write 133337 that memory location
下一个字节写到0x133338
you will write the next byte to 133338
之后是39，3a...
and the 9 10
这是一个尴尬的错误
and this is an embarrassing error
因为又错了
because this is not right again
好吧，我改一下
all right let me fix that
好吧
all right
现在改完了
and now it's fixed okay
抱歉，算错了，没按16进制算
sorry I had this I have hex fail
总之
anyways
它会写入8字节，从133337写到13333f
it'll write the 8 bytes from 133337 to 13333f
很酷
pretty cool okay
现在
now
我们讨论一下如何控制写入大小
let's talk about controlling those write sizes
你完全可以控制写入大小
you can absolutely control those write sizes
你可以用部分标识符
you can use partial
我移一下到这里
let me move myself here
你可以用寄存器的部分标识
you can use partial registers
很容易就能写更少的字节数
very easy to write fewer bytes
这条指令会加载
so this instruction will load
这两条指令会
these two instructions will load 8 bytes
从12345开始的内存地址，加载8字节到RBX
from the memory location starting at 12345 into RBX
然后写8字节（口误）
and then write 8 bytes
写入4字节，ebx
write four of those bytes from EBX
到0x133337开始的内存
into the memory location starting at 133337
EBX是一个4字节，32位长的寄存器
EBX is a 4 byte long 32 bit long register
将ebx写入到内存时，会写入4字节
when you write from EBX you will write those 4 bytes
很直接
super straightforward
这个，存储8位，就1字节，AH
this stores 8 bits just one byte AH
就是那个部分寄存器
just that partial register
好吧
all right
抱歉
sorry it'll load
什么鬼，全是错的
what the heck man this is full of mistakes
抱歉，稍等
I apologize one second
好了
all right
十分抱歉
apologize about that
这将从地址0x12345加载8位数据到bh
this will load 8 bits from the address 0x12345 to bh
只有8位，因为BH是8位宽的寄存器
just 8 bits because BH is an 8 bit wide register
只加载1字节
just one byte load
好吧，别忘了
all right don't forget
如果你加载数据到EAX, EBX，等等
if you load into EAX EBX etc etc
会将对应寄存器的高32位清零
you will zero out the top 32 bits
你会忘记它的，然后被它搞到
you will forget and it'll screw you up
这一点都不好玩
and it's not fun
好的
okay so
现在我们讨论了指定大小地写入
now we're talking about all of these sized writes
但他们很奇怪
well they are really weird
在x86以及大多数现代架构上
on x86 as well as most modern operating systems
数据是以字节为单位逆序存储的
data is stored backwards byte wides
即所谓的小端序
and something called little endian
这里rax中的c001 ca75
so here we have cool cats being set to rax
很酷
very awesome
我们把c001 ca75
we write Cool Cats
写入到0x10000这个地址
into hex 10,000 this address
顺序是反的
it ends up backwards
它是用小端序写的
it's written in little endian
第一个字节，如果你只读取一个字节的话
the first byte if you wanted to read it
会是75
would end up with 75
就是ts
that's ts
然后是ca
then ca the next byte backwards
然后01
then 01
然后c0
and then co
c0 01 ca 75 翻转了一下
cool cats gets flipped around
每次你在寄存器和内存间多字节写入
any time you do a multiple byte write between registers and memory
你的数据都会翻转
your data gets flipped
只有这一种情况
that's the only time
为什么会这样
why does this happen
它是由于一些有根据的历史原因
it happens for historical reasons that are rooted in something that makes sense
英特尔发明8008处理器
so Intel created the 8008 processor
一个古老的处理器
an ancient ancient processor
一切的前身
predecessor to everything else
于1972年
in 1972
不是一切，就是所有intel系列处理器的前身
not everything else but all the other Intel stuff
他们是为了一家叫datapoint的公司创造的
they created for a company called Data Point
为了兼容datapoint的现有流程
and to be compatible with Data Points its existing processes
它们使用了相同的端序
they use the same endianess
这很聪明
and it's clever
如果你想做加法
if you wanted to add
想一下在小学做的加法
consider doing like an elementary school long addition
写下一个数字
you write out a number
再写一个数字
you write it out another number
然后开始加
and you add
从最右边开始
and you start on the right
算到左边
and you work to the left
你从最低有效位开始
you start at the least significant digits
往最高有效位计算
and you work toward the more significant digits
你这么做的原因是
and the reason you do that is
在你加的过程中
as you add that things
如果一列的计算结果大于10
if the result of your addition on the column is greater than 10
就进一位
you carry a 1
然后继续这样做
and then you keep doing that
事实证明这更容易做
and turns out that's easier to do
只能从最低有效位开始往上加
it's only possible to do if you start from the least significant and move upwards
如果你要处理数据
so if you are going to process data
加一些大数
and add large numbers
这就解释了为什么逆序存储在内存中
it makes sense you start you store them backwards in memory
先从最低有效字节开始计算
you start with the least significant byte
再继续
and you go onwards
从历史上看
historically
根据维基百科
according to Wikipedia
我就是在这里看到的
which is where I track this down to
这就是Intel的8008存储多字节值时使用小端序的原因
that's why Intel went with little endian for 8008 for multi byte values
从那时到现代x86的每一步演变
and every step of the evolution since then up to modern x86
都至少与前一代保持了兼容
has at least kept compatibility with its direct predecessor
所以有一定兼容性
and so there's some level compatibility
包括了内存端序
including the memory endianess
小端序数据还有其他好处
now there's other benefits of little endian data etc etc
这就是一个已经做出的选择
but it's a choice that is made
我们活在其中
and that's the choice we live in
所以现在数据在内存中是逆序存储的
so data is going to be stored backwards in memory now
提醒一下，这只会发生在
caveats again this only happens
这可能不是完全正确的，但总之
this probably isn't true globally but whatever
通常这种情况只发生在
typically this only happens
寄存器和内存间，一次存储或加载多字节数据的时候
when storing and loading multiple bytes between registers and memory at a time
它只发生在字节级别
it only happens on the byte level
只是字节被倒过来了
just the bytes get flipped backwards
字节中的单个比特保持不变
the individual bits in the bytes stay intact
这里是co，这里还是co
so co here is co here
不会翻转比特位
you don't flip the bits
存储和加载多字节这种事人们常做
that's a very very common thing that people do
还有压栈和弹栈
and pushes and pops
完全一样
exactly the same
push将一次写入8个字节
a push will write 8 bytes
它会反过来写
and it will write them in reverse
酷
awesome
人们经常混淆这一点
and people often confuse that
因为栈已经是反向增长了
because the stack is already growing in reverse
如你所期望的
as to what you'd expect
栈会向更小的内存地址增长
it's going towards smaller amounts of memory smaller addresses
所以人们会觉得
and so people yeah but like
但不对
but no
压入一个8字节数据，rsp会减小，而数据按小端序写入内存
it's going to  ?? and memory and things get pushed backwards
好酷
okay cool
就和其他内存访问一样
like any other memory access
好了，这就是端序
all right that's endianess
我们来谈谈地址计算
let's talk about address calculation
汇编中，准确说x86架构下二进制中
well it's assembly or really the x86 architecture in binary
所以非常类似汇编
and so very similar to ??  assembly
能你做地址计算
allows you to do address calculations
它对访问复杂结构很有用
so it's useful for like accessing complex structures
多组数据等等
lists of data etc etc
这里我们用rax作为栈中的索引
here we use rax as an index into the stack
一次访问8字节
8 bytes at a time
首先把rax设为0
so first we set it to zero
这是栈顶的数据
this is the data right at the stack pointer
再设rax为1
we set it to 1
这是下一个元素
this is the next entry
我们可以继续增加rax
and we can continue incrementing it
依次类推
and so on
如果对栈计算的没错，你能确定目标元素的索引
you can figure out if your stack calculations are correct
或者就是想获得什么东西的地址
or if you just really want to get a memory address for something else
可以用加载有效地址（LEA）指令
by using the load effective address instruction LEA
LEA能让你
load effective address allows you
完成同样的操作
to specify that same operation
由于某种原因，这里我加了5
this one I for some reason put a plus 5
这可能是一个bug
because presumably that's a bug
把地址放到这里
to load it in there
然后你可以检查它
and then you can inspect it
做你想做的
and do whatever you want with it
传递给函数
and pass it around to functions
都很有趣
and it's all great fun
现在
now
地址计算有限制
address calculation has limits
你不能做任意算术
you can't just do arbitrary arithmetic in it
它需要在CPU上被编码成非常有限的指令
it needs to be encoded into a very limited instruction on the CPU
基本上就是拿一个寄存器
you basically take register
加上一个寄存器乘以2或4或8
plus a register times either 2 or 4 or 8
再加上一个值
plus a value
只能做这些算术
that's all you get
但这已经足够了
but it's typically good enough alright
现在
now
AMD64的地址计算中有一件很酷的事
one of the very cool things while you talking about address calculations that AMD64 did
是它引入了rip相对寻址
is introduce rip relative addressing
回想一下，rip是指令指针
recall that rip is the instruction pointer
它指向下一条要执行的指令
it points to the next instruction that will be executed
以后讨论控制流时，会讨论更多的rip相关事项
and we'll talk more about rip when we talk about how to change control flow
说到LEA
load effective address
你不能直接读取RIP的值
you can't move data out of the instruction pointer directly
你不能直接说嘿
you can't just say hey
下一条指令的地址是什么
what's the address of the next instruction
这不是mov指令能做的
it just isn't something the mov instruction does
它不支持
it just wasn't supported
而LEA
load effective address
能访问64位x86上的指令指针
is able to access the instruction pointer on 64 bit x86
所以当你想知道
and so when you want to know
下一条指令的地址是什么
hey what's the address of the next instruction
你可以这么做
you can do this
把它加载到rax
and you can load it into rax
你还可以对它做地址计算
you can also do arbitrary address operations with indexing
就像我们在前一页所做的那样
exactly what we did in the previous page
乘以8，乘以2之类的
multiplying by 8 by 2 whatever
而且聪明的AMD
also AMD in their infinite wisdom
在x86基础上设计amd64
when they designed amd64 out of x86
并给我们带来了64位架构时
and gave us this 64 bit architecture
这很伟大
that's awesome
还允许我们直接访问rip指向的内存
allowed us also to directly access memory offset from the instruction
甚至往里写数据
now even writing there right
这里有一个警告
now there's a caveat here
你将在shellcoding模块中了解到
as you will learn in the shellcoding module
内存通常不是
memory isn't typically
存储代码的内存通常不能被写入
memory that holds code isn't typically able to be written to
但有能写的情况
but if it can it can
你能基于rip，做间接寻址
or you can offset it from the code
事实上，这个rip相对寻址
in fact this rip relative addressing enables
对在代码周围嵌入数据，非常有用
super useful when you embed data around your code
每个现代二进制都这么做
which every modern binary does explicitly
一个ELF文件
an ELF file
包括它的数据和代码
including its data and its code
实际上是作为一个大块加载到内存中的
is actually loaded into memory as a big chunk
由于我们可以做rip相对寻址
and the fact that we can do rip relative addressing
又因为我们知道文件的大小
because we know the size of the file
知道数据相对于代码的位置
we know where relative to code the data is
所以现在可以访问数据了
you can now get at the data
这就实现了很酷的安全特性
and this enables cool security features
比如可以把二进制文件随机放到内存的任何地方
like being able to put that file anywhere in memory at random
而不影响它的功能
and still have it function
因为它不依赖于一个特定的地址
because it doesn't rely on a specific address to beyond
所有的访问都是相对于rip的
all accesses are relative to where it's executing
非常酷，一个强大的现代安全功能
very cool and a powers modern security features
很酷
cool
这就是rip相对寻址
so that's rip relative addressing
现在
now
你可以向内存写入立即数
you can write immediate values to memory
但是你必须指定它们的大小
but you must specify their size
因为CPU不知道0x1337要占多大
because the CPU doesn't know how big 0x1337 is
它可能知道
it knows  it could potential know
汇编器，实际上不是CPU
the assembler actually not the CPU
汇编器不知道
the assembler doesn't know
这条指令该告诉cpu做什么
what instruction taught but what to tell the CPU to do
它是该告诉CPU写入00001337
it could is it telling the CPU to write 00001337
还是说写入4个字节
or is it telling that 4 bytes
或者告诉CPU写入2字节1337呢
or is it telling the CPU to write 2 bytes 1337
2个不同的指令
2 different instructions
两种不同的二进制表示
two different representations in binary
所以你可以显示指定一个大小
and so you can specify a size
你可以说嘿
you can say hey
Rax目前是双字指针
rax is currently a double word pointer
它指向一个双字
it's pointing to a double word
所以写入4字节
so write 4 bytes
取决于你的汇编器
depending on your assembler
可能写作DWORD，而不是DWORD PTR
it might want DWORD instead of DWORD PTR
或QWORD
or QWORD
或WORD
or WORD
这就是它们的原理
that's how these work
我会在后面的shellcoding中讲到它
and I actually have that later in the shellcoding
因为在那里更相关
because that's where it becomes a little more relevant
好吧
all right
最后，栈并不是唯一的内存区域
and finally the stack isn't the only memory region
还有其他的内存区域，我们稍后会学到
there are other memory regions that we'll learn about later
或者我猜是栈
or I guess the stack
或者用rip相对寻址可以访问到的二进制代码
or your binary code which is accessible with rip relative addressing
栈可以通过push pop和RSP寻址来访问
the stack is accessible with push pop and addressing into RSP
还有其他的内存区域
well there are other memory regions
你可以在程序中申请分配内存
and you can also allocate other memories in your program
我们稍后再谈
we'll talk about that later
希望你们对内存了解很多了
hopefully you know a lot about memory
再见
see you next time